- [Ken] Now, I'm gonna turn on 2000 volts.
- [Derek] What?
And this is the first step
in creating snowflakes in the lab.
This is totally wild.
What? - Crazy, huh?
The tips of those needles are
like a hundred nanometers in diameter.
- [Derek] That is so wild.
Dr. Ken Libbrecht is the snowflake guy.
- I was the snowflake consultant for the movie, "Frozen."
It's okay to conjure snowflakes out of your fingertips,
but they have to be real snowflakes,
or people aren't buying it.
The US Post Office made snowflake stamps using my pictures.
It's not the kind of thing you normally think of
when you start doing physics,
that you'd be on a postage stamp.
- [Derek] You've written the book on snowflakes, literally.
- So I had like two successful books in a row,
so we just kept making books,
until finally  they sold zero copies,
and then we stopped.
- So, are you kind of like a snowflake artist?
- I call it a designer snowflake.
Because yes, I am designing this on the fly.
I don't have a computer that does all this for me.
I just do it by hand, so every one's a little different.
- [Derek] Ken knows so much about snowflakes,
he can design and construct them to his own specifications.
- [Ken] So what's happening now is it's growing
and doing its thing at some...
It's at -13 Celsius now, but I want to make some branches.
I'll just turn this down to -15.
And then I'm gonna increase the humidity a little bit,
the super saturation,
and you'll start to see branches come out there.
- [Derek] See you changing those conditions,
just caused the plate to kind of stop and become really--
- I changed the growth conditions to prefer branches.
This little thing right there, that little nub,
that's the only thing that touches the sapphire substrate.
The rest of this is all growing above.
This increases the air flow.
Those are droplets forming,
and now I'm really kicking it into gear.
Now, what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna turn that humidity down to zero,
so the droplets are starting to recede,
and this will stop growing
and kind of start to facet a little bit.
Let's say I want branches again,
now I'm gonna really hammer on it.
- [Derek] So you're giving it a lot of moisture.
- A lot of moisture now, but you'll see side branches.
You really start to feel you understand what's going on,
when you can say, "Now I'm gonna do this,"
and then it happens.
It's fun. I can predict the future.
I like to think they're better than nature,
and the reason is that the facets of just sharp.
All the edges on these things are just sharp and crisp,
whereas in the sky they have to fall,
and by the time they fall, and you pick them up,
and you put them under a microscope,
they've started to evaporate a little.
Boy, these are just,  bang, just crisp.
- [Derek] The first close-up photograph of a snowflake
in the wild was taken in 1885
by American meteorologist, Wilson A. Bentley.
It was Bentley who originated the idea
that no two snowflakes are alike, and he would know.
Over the course of his life,
he took more than 5,000 photos of snowflakes,
a selection of which appear in his book, "Snow Crystals,"
which is still in print today.
But most snowflakes don't look
like the ones Bentley photographed,
because he selected only those in pristine condition
with uncommon beauty and symmetry.
- I mean, when you're looking for snowflakes,
I'll take a big piece of cardboard,
and you just glance at it.
Crap, nothing, brush them aside, more.
No, each brush is a thousand snowflakes.
They're hard to find.
They're one in a million, I mean, literally.
- [Derek] We are all so used to seeing pictures like this,
that we are blind to the mysteries of the snowflake.
Like, why do they all have six fold, radial symmetry?
Why are they so intricate,
and yet so different from each other?
How do opposite arms of a snowflake
mirror each other so perfectly?
I mean, how does one side of the snowflake know
what the other side is doing?
And why are snowflakes flat?
They're usually millimeters in diameter,
but micro meters thick.
The edges of a plate can be as narrow as razorblades,
but the mystery goes even deeper.
Everyone pictures snowflakes like this,
but the truth is they take all sorts of different forms,
like this, a hollow column.
That is a snowflake?
- [Dr. Libbrecht] That is a snowflake.
- [Derek] There are also needles, cups and bullets.
- This is like my favorite kind of snowflake.
It is a capped column.
It started out growing as a column,
but then the temperature changed,
and then you've got plates growing on either end.
It's just a cacophony of different shapes.
All of these appear spontaneously.
There's no DNA or any kind of a blueprint
for what's going on.
It's just water vapor freezing into ice,
and all this happens.
- [Derek] So you've identified
35 different types of snowflakes.
- Yes, there's no really one way
to define a type of snowflake.
The first chart of snowflakes is like 41, I think,
and then it got bigger - 60 or 70,
and the latest one by some Japanese physicists,
I think had 108 different types of snowflakes,
and I found 108 was too many.
- [Derek] How does simple ice create so many distinct forms?
平平无奇的冰为何能产生变化万千的形态呢
All snowflakes form in much the same way.
各种雪花生成的方式基本相同
Water evaporates into water vapor,
水蒸发形成水蒸气
individual molecules bouncing around in the atmosphere,
孤立的分子在大气中弹跳
and as this vapor rises,
随着蒸气上升
it cools and becomes super saturated,
这些分子冷却并转变成过饱和状态
meaning there are more water molecules in the air
意味着这时空气中的水分子的数量多于
than there would be in equilibrium at this temperature.
相同温度下平衡状态的水分子数量
Water molecules condense onto dust particles
水分子在尘埃颗粒上凝聚
to form tiny droplets.
产生微小的水滴
And although the temperature may be below freezing,
尽管环境温度可能低于水的凝固点
the droplets don't immediately freeze,
这些水滴不会立即冻结
but at some point, one droplet will freeze.
但是在某个位置  一滴水可能会冷凝
Inside, the water molecules lock into place,
微观上  其中的水分子被固定在位置上
forming a hexagonal crystal.
形成一个六方晶体
This structure results from the peculiarities of water molecules.
这种结构源自水分子的特性
Oxygen atoms attract electrons more than hydrogen.
氧原子吸引电子的能力比氢原子强
And since the molecule has a bent shape,
又因为水分子本身成V形
it's polar with oxygen being slightly negative,
所以会极化  在氧原子一端略带负电
and the hydrogens, slightly positive.
氢原子一端则略带正电
Since unlike charges attract, hydrogen from one molecule
由于异号电荷相吸引  一个水分子中的氢原子
will sit next to an oxygen from another molecule,
会靠近另一个水分子中的氧原子
forming a so-called hydrogen bond,
产生所谓的氢键
and this is what creates the hexagonal molecular lattice.
正是这种相互作用  让分子形成了六边形的晶格
But how does this microscopic lattice
但是这样的微观晶格
grow into a hexagonal crystal that we can see?
是如何生长为我们所见的六方晶体的呢
- So you start with a chunk of ice,
假定起初有一小块冰晶
and these little guys are meant to be water molecules.
这些小家伙就代表水分子
And what happens is there are these flat surfaces,
现在  看这些平坦的界面（即晶体的刻面）
which are the facet surfaces,
and at a molecular scale, they're very smooth and flat.
在分子尺度上  它们非常光滑、平整
And so when a molecule hits,
当一个分子撞上去
a water vapor molecule hits that smooth and flat surface,
一个水蒸气分子  撞击这个平整而光滑的界面时
it tends to bounce off.
它会被反弹
Whereas here, it's rough,
而这些地方较为粗糙
there are a lot of dangling molecular bonds over here.
所以会有很多自由分子在那里成键
That's a rough surface.
这是个粗糙的界面
And so when these molecules hit, they tend to stick.
所以如果分子撞击晶体 它们更倾向凝结在此处
It's a statistical thing, of course,
这当然是统计意义上的结论
but the probabilities are high that they stick here
但分子固定在这里的概率较高
and low that they stick here.
而固定在这里的概率较低
So if you take any shape, and you just let it grow
所以  如果随便选一种形状的冰晶  任其生长
for a little while, the rough areas fill in,
只要一小会儿  这些崎岖的位置就会被填满
and the flat areas don't grow very fast,
而平坦的位置不会生长太快
and you end up with a faceted shape.
这样最终就得到了一个多面体的形状
- [Derek] And that's how we get from the quantum mechanics
我们根据量子力学推演出了
that governs a water molecule, to a hexagonal prism of ice.
一个水分子如何变为六棱柱形状的冰
This prism has two basal facets and six prism facets,
六棱柱有两个底面和六个侧面
which is important.
这很重要
If the basal facets grow fast, you get a column.
如果底面长得快  就会得到柱状的雪花
If the prism facets grow faster, you get a flat snowflake.
如果棱柱的侧面生长更快  则会得到片状的雪花
Once there is a seed crystal,
一旦某处有一个晶种
nearby water droplets evaporate
附近的液滴将蒸发产生水蒸气分子
and deposit water molecules onto the growing snowflake.
这些分子会再度凝结在生长中的雪花上
Since the corners of the hexagonal prism stick out farther into humid air,
由于六方晶体的棱角与潮湿空气接触更充分
they grow faster,
它们生长得更快
and now they extend even farther,
现在它们以伸展到更远处
so they grow even faster in a positive feedback loop.
这种正反馈机制使得它们生长得更快
This gives rise to six radial branches.
由此就产生了辐射状的六簇分支
At the corners of these branches,
在这些分支的棱角上
additional branches can form for the same reason.
新的分支也会基于相同的原理生成
Around a hundred thousand droplets are required
大约需要十万滴水
to make a single snowflake,
才能产生一片雪花
and the process usually takes 30 to 45 minutes.
整个过程会经过大约 30 到 45 分钟
In the 1930s, Ukichiro Nakaya
was systematically studying snowflakes
at the University of Hokkaido in Japan.
He discovered that the different types of snowflakes
don't all occur under the same conditions.
Instead, two factors,
the temperature and level of super saturation
determine what type of snowflake grows.
His findings are summarized in the Nakaya Diagram,
but it's not a simple pattern.
Around -2 Celsius, you get plates.
At -5 Celsius, columns and needles form.
At -15 Celsius, it's plates again,
and then below -20, you get columns and plates.
The Nakaya Diagram allows us
to understand a rough history of any snowflake.
Does each snowflake in essence reveal its history
through its shape?
- Yeah, absolutely, to some degree.
You can definitely look at a snowflake and say,
"Yeah, I know what conditions
"that crystal grew under, more or less."
Your typical weather patterns, fronts, cold front,
that produces a lot of capped columns,
because as the cloud moves up, it starts to get colder
and initially start to freeze at around -6, -10.
That makes columns, and as it gets colder,
then it makes branches and plates,
and so you get capped columns.
- [Derek] This also explains
why snowflakes are so intricate.
The temperature and humidity at each moment of growth
determines the structures formed in that moment.
The symmetry you see is not because one side
somehow knows what the other side is doing,
but because both sides of a single snowflake grow
in the exact same conditions.
- When the crystal changes its position,
the temperature will change, say,
and all six branches will see the same temperature change,
and so they'll all respond the same way.
- [Derek] Different snowflakes, on the other hand,
each take a unique path,
and therefore they experience a unique set of conditions,
which is why no two snowflakes are alike.
But in the lab, you can carefully control the conditions,
但在这个实验中  你可以精细地控制条件
so theoretically it should be possible
所以理论上说
to create almost identical snowflakes,
制造几乎一模一样的雪花是有可能的
and indeed, Ken has.
事实上  Ken确实可以
What's in here?
这里面是什么
- Poke your flashlight in there, and you'll see.
把手电筒伸进去  你会看见的
- [Derek] Ah ha, I'm imagining these are seed crystals of a sort?
啊哈  我想这些是某种晶种吧
- [Ken] Those are a little sparkly snow crystals.
这是一些发光的雪晶
- [Derek] Yeah.
哦
- You know this is another little chamber.
这是另一种意义上的小房间
It's just a cold plate,
这是一个冷却台
and there's a little sapphire disc in there,
这里面有一张小蓝宝石碟片
and then I'm going to push this thing, my sapphire,
然后我要把我的蓝宝石推进去
all the way in here, and the crystals will waft onto to it
这些晶体就会飘到上面去
and hopefully stay there.
大概率它们会待在这
The idea popped in, it's like,
这个想法大概是这样出现的
oh, if I grow two next to one another,
如果我把两片雪花放在相邻的位置
they'll be kind of identical,
它们就会有点类似
and I call them identical twin snowflakes,
我把它们称为同卵双胞胎雪花
'cause they're like identical twin people.
因为它们就像是同卵双胞胎
They're not exactly the same,
它们并不是完全一样的
but clearly more alike than you would ever expect.
但很显然比你预期的要相似很多
Is it really true that no two snowflakes are alike?
没有两片雪花是相似的  这句话真的是对的吗
You know, that's just a silly question.
你也知道这问题挺愚蠢的
It's silly because no two trees are like,
因为没有两棵一模一样的树
no two grains of sand are like, no two anything are alike.
没有两粒一样的沙  没有两个事物是一模一样的
Anything that has any complexity
只要某个事物存在复杂性
is different from everything else,
就会与其他事物不同
because once you introduce complexity,
因为一旦涉及到复杂性
then there's just an uncountable number of ways to make it.
创造这项事物的途径就不可胜数
- [Derek] If a pair of twins snowflakes
如果一对“双胞胎”雪花
are growing too close together,
生长的地方特别近
they end up competing for moisture between them,
它们会竞争二者间的水分
stunting both of their growths.
最终同时阻碍了它们的生长
The Nakaya Diagram allows us to understand a lot
中谷图表可以让我们
about snowflake formation.
更好地理解雪花的形成
Ken has used his experiments
Ken通过自己的实验
to build his own version of the chart.
建立了他自己的图表
But what it doesn't explain
但这并没有解释
is why do ice crystals form this way in the first place?
为什么冰晶最初是这样形成的
I mean, why do we get plates and then columns
也就是  为什么会先产生片状的雪花  然后是柱状
and then plates and columns again?
之后又是片状  最后又是柱状
This has been a mystery,
这早就是一个谜团了
essentially since Nakaya introduced his diagram back in the 1930s,
可以追溯到上世纪30年代  提出中谷图表的时候
but Ken believes he now has an answer.
不过Ken相信  他已得到答案了
Anytime you have a crystal,
假设你有一个（单）晶体
the reason why you get these smooth flat facets
它之所以有光滑平整的切面
is because it's not easy to grow more crystal on top.
是因为顶面很难继续生长晶体了
There are so-called nucleation barriers.
这就是所谓的成核势垒
What you need is a critical density of additional molecules
你需要知道这种物质的其他分子的临界密度
of the substance before they can come together
达到临界密度后它们会聚集在一起
to form a little island that is stable enough to grow
形成一个足够稳定的小岛
and add another layer onto the crystal.
并叠加在晶体上面
When you're first forming a snowflake,
第一次生成雪花时
you're always gonna start with a hexagonal prism
你总是会从一个六角棱柱开始
with its two basal facets
它有两个底面
and six prism facets around the side.
和六个侧面
And the nucleation barrier for the basal facets
底面的成核势垒
is different than that of the prism facets.
与侧面的成核势垒是不同的
If the nucleation barrier is lower for the prism facets,
如果侧面的成核势垒比较低
then they grow faster, and you get plate like structures.
侧面就会生长得更快  最终得到片状结构
If the nucleation barrier is lower for the basal facets,
如果底面的成核势垒比较低
then they grow faster,
底面就会生长得更快
and you end up with column-like structures.
最终得到柱状结构
Now, the nucleation barriers of ice
are known as a function of temperature,
and this explains why around -2,
the prism facets grow faster, and you get plates,
because their nucleation barrier is lower.
You can also see why below -20 or so,
well then you get columns,
because the basal facet nucleation barrier is lower
at those temperatures.
But what doesn't make sense is why we should get columns
at around -5 Celsius and then plates again at -15.
So what is happening?
Well Ken's hypothesis is that these nucleation barriers
are valid only for large flat facets,
but if you had really narrow facets,
well, the nucleation barriers would be different.
So Ken proposes that narrow basal facets
have a dip in their nucleation barrier around -4 Celsius,
and narrow prism facets have a dip at -15,
so his hypothesis is that the graph should look like this.
This then is consistent with all the different forms
of snowflakes that grow at different temperatures.
But what accounts for these dips?
Well, let's say we have a narrow prism facet,
so we're growing a plate snowflake.
Water molecules that hit the basal facets
are unlikely to reach the critical density required
to overcome the nucleation barrier,
so that surface grows only slowly.
But on either side of this narrow prism facet,
water molecules can stick on the rough edges,
and to minimize surface energy,
the ideal shape of this face would be semicircular.
But if only the top few layers of water molecules are mobile
to try to lower the surface energy,
many of them diffuse onto the prism facet
and in the process,
they exceed the critical density required
to overcome the nucleation barrier,
and so they can grow the crystal on the prism facet.
So due to this narrow edge, the nucleation barrier
is effectively lower than it would be
for a large prism facet.
A similar effect happens for the basal facets,
just at a different temperature.
And Ken has done experiments to investigate
whether these effects are observed in the lab.
- And so I did a series of experiments using that apparatus
and man, it's just like, boom, just like that.
Whoa!
When you make a model,
and you sort of find it's supposed to do something,
and it sorta does, it's just like, this might be right!
- So far, the results agree nicely with the hypothesis.
So after 85 years, maybe we now understand
the molecular physics of ice well enough
to finally explain why snowflakes grow
into such a diverse collection
of columnar and plate-like forms.
- And I've done a lot of my career
in astronomy and astrophysics.
Nobody ever asks you what it's good for, I mean, never.
Not even once did anyone say,
"What are those black holes gonna be used for?" No,
Saturn's rings, "Why do you care about Saturn's rings?
"What's the motivation for studying Saturn,"
nobody asks that.
Every time I give a talk, people are like,
"What are you doing? What on earth is this for?"
I'll tell you the real reason,
the real reason that I got into this.
You look at a snowflake and you kind of go,
"Um, actually,  we don't have any idea
"how that works."
Well, that doesn't work.
We have to know how that works, dammit!
Well, I want to be the guy
that figures out how snowflakes work.
That's always been a driver.
You know, as a scientist, you want to figure something out.